so I wouldn't be the one left in the field. My eyes clenched tighter so I wouldn't see the wheat being separated from the chaff. And then a voice rang out above us: "Amen." It was over. I looked at the clock. It was after midnight. I looked at the elder believers whose savior had not come, who were too proud to show any signs of disappointment, who had believed too much and for too long to start doubting now. But I was upset on their behalf. They had been duped, hoodwinked, bamboozled, and I had gone right along with them. I had prayed their prayers, I had yielded not to temptation as best I could. I had dipped my head not once, but twice in that snot-inducing baptism pool. I had believed. Now what? I got home just in time to turn on the television and watch Peter Jennings announce the new millennium as it rolled in around the world. It struck me that it would have been strange anyway, for Jesus to come back again and again based on the different time zones. (Laughter) And this made me feel even more ridiculous -- hurt, really. But there on that night, I did not stop believing. I just believed a new thing: that it was possible not to believe. It was possible the answers I had were wrong, that the questions themselves were wrong. And now, where there was once a mountain of certitude, there was, running right down to its foundation, a spring of doubt, a spring that promised rivers. I can trace the whole drama of my life back to that night in that church when my savior did not come for me; when the thing I believed most certainly turned out to be, if not a lie, then not quite the truth. And even though most of you prepared for Y2K in a very different way, I'm convinced that you are here because some part of you has done the same thing that I have done since the dawn of this new century, since my mother left and my father stayed away and my Lord refused to come. And I held out my hand, reaching for something to believe in. I held on when I arrived at Yale at 18, with the faith that my journey from Oak Cliff, Texas was a chance to leave behind all the challenges I had known, the broken dreams and broken bodies I had seen. But when I found myself back home one winter break, with my face planted in the floor, my hands tied behind my back and a burglar's gun pressed to my head, I knew that even the best education couldn't save me. I held on when I showed up at Lehman Brothers as an intern in 2008. (Laughter) So hopeful -- that I called home to inform my family that we'd never be poor again. (Laughter) But as I witnessed this temple of finance come crashing down before my eyes, I knew that even the best job couldn't save me. I held on when I showed up in Washington DC as a young staffer, who had heard a voice call out from Illinois, saying, "It's been a long time coming, but in this election, change has come to America." But as the Congress ground to a halt and the country ripped at the seams and hope and change began to feel like a cruel joke, I knew that even the political second coming could not save me. I had knelt faithfully at the altar of the American Dream, praying to the gods of my time of success, and money, and power. But over and over again, midnight struck, and I opened my eyes to see that all of these gods were dead. And from that graveyard, I began the search once more, not because I was brave, but because I knew that I would either believe or I would die. So I took a pilgrimage to yet another mecca, Harvard Business School -- (Laughter) this time, knowing that I could not simply accept the salvation that it claimed to offer. No, I knew there'd be more work to do. The work began in the dark corner of a crowded party, in the late night of an early, miserable Cambridge winter, when three friends and I asked a question that young folks searching for something real have asked for a very long time: "What if we took a road trip?" (Laughter) We didn't know where'd we go or how we'd get there, but we knew we had to do it. Because all our lives we yearned, as Jack Kerouac wrote, to "sneak out into the night and disappear somewhere," and go find out what everybody was doing all over the country. So even though there were other voices who said that the risk was too great and the proof too thin, we went on anyhow. We went on 8,000 miles across America in the summer of 2013, through the cow pastures of Montana, through the desolation of Detroit, through the swamps of New Orleans, where we found and worked with men and women who were building small businesses that made purpose their bottom line. And having been trained at the West Point of capitalism, this struck us as a revolutionary idea. (Laughter) And this idea spread, growing into a nonprofit called MBAs Across America, a movement that landed me here on this stage today. It spread because we found a great hunger in our generation for purpose, for meaning. It spread because we found countless entrepreneurs in the nooks and crannies of America who were creating jobs and changing lives and who needed a little help. But if I'm being honest, it also spread because I fought to spread it. There was no length to which I would not go to preach this gospel, to get more people to believe that we could bind the wounds of a broken country, one social business at a time. But it was this journey of evangelism that led me to the rather different gospel that I've come to share with you today. It began one evening almost a year ago at the Museum of Natural History in New York City, at a gala for alumni of Harvard Business School. Under a full-size replica of a whale, I sat with the titans of our time as they celebrated their peers and their good deeds. There was pride in a room where net worth and assets under management surpassed half a trillion dollars. We looked over all that we had made, and it was good. (Laughter) But it just so happened, two days later, I had to travel up the road to Harlem, where I found myself sitting in an urban farm that had once been a vacant lot, listening to a man named Tony tell me of the kids that showed up there every day. All of them lived below the poverty line. Many of them carried all of their belongings in a backpack to avoid losing them in a homeless shelter. Some of them came to Tony's program, called Harlem Grown, to get the only meal they had each day. Tony told me that he started Harlem Grown with money from his pension, after 20 years as a cab driver. He told me that he didn't give himself a salary, because despite success, the program struggled for resources. He told me that he would take any help that he could get. And I was there as that help. But as I left Tony, I felt the sting and salt of tears welling up in my eyes. I felt the weight of revelation that I could sit in one room on one night, where a few hundred people had half a trillion dollars, and another room, two days later, just 50 blocks up the road, where a man was going without a salary to get a child her only meal of the day. And it wasn't the glaring inequality that made me want to cry, it wasn't the thought of hungry, homeless kids, it wasn't rage toward the one percent or pity toward the 99. No, I was disturbed because I had finally realized that I was the dialysis for a country that needed a kidney transplant. I realized that my story stood in for all those who were expected to pick themselves up by their bootstraps, even if they didn't have any boots; that my organization stood in for all the structural, systemic help that never went to Harlem or Appalachia or the Lower 9th Ward; that my voice stood in for all those voices that seemed too unlearned, too unwashed, too unaccommodated. And the shame of that, that shame washed over me like the shame of sitting in front of the television, watching Peter Jennings announce the new millennium again and again and again. I had been duped, hoodwinked, bamboozled. But this time, the false savior was me. You see, I've come a long way from that altar on the night I thought the world would end, from a world where people spoke in tongues and saw suffering as a necessary act of God and took a text to be infallible truth. Yes, I've come so far that I'm right back where I started. Because it simply is not true to say that we live in an age of disbelief -- no, we believe today just as much as any time that came before. Some of us may believe in the prophecy of Brené Brown or Tony Robbins. We may believe in the bible of The New Yorker or the Harvard Business Review. We may believe most deeply when we worship right here at the church of TED, but we desperately want to believe, we need to believe. We speak in the tongues of charismatic leaders that promise to solve all our problems. We see suffering as a necessary act of the capitalism that is our god, we take the text of technological progress to be infallible truth. And we hardly realize the human price we pay when we fail to question one brick, because we fear it might shake our whole foundation. But if you are disturbed by the unconscionable things that we have come to accept, then it must be questioning time. So I have not a gospel of disruption or innovation or a triple bottom line. I do not have a gospel of faith to share with you today, in fact. I have and I offer a gospel of doubt.
así no sería el abandonado en el campo. Mis ojos muy cerrados así no vería al trigo siendo separado de la cizaña. Y luego una voz resonó sobre nosotros: «Amén». Se había terminado. Miré al reloj. Era más de medianoche. Miré a los feligreses Mayores cuyo salvador no apareció; eran muy orgullosos para mostrar su desilusión; habían creído demasiado y por mucho tiempo para empezar a dudar ahora. Pero yo me sentía mal por ellos. Habían sido engañados, embaucados, burlados y yo había pasado por lo mismo que ellos. Había hecho sus oraciones, había resistido a la tentación tanto como pude. había sumergido mi cabeza no una, sino dos veces, irritando mi nariz en esa pila bautismal. Yo había creído. ¿Ahora qué? Regresé a casa justo a tiempo para encender el televisor y ver a Peter Jennings anunciar el nuevo milenio que entraba en curso en el mundo. Se me ocurrió que, de alguna forma, habría sido extraño que Jesús regresara una y otra vez basado en todas las zonas horarias. (Risas) Y esto me hizo sentir aún más ridículo, herido, en realidad. Pero allí en esa noche, no dejé de creer. Sólo creía una cosa nueva: que era posible no creer. Era posible que las respuestas estuvieran mal, que las mismas preguntas fueran equivocadas. Y ahora, donde una vez hubo una montaña de fe, surgía justo bajo sus cimientos, un manantial de duda, Un manantial que presagiaba ríos. Puedo dar al origen del drama de mi vida en esa noche en aquella iglesia cuando mi salvador no vino por mí, cuando lo que creía con tanta certeza resultó ser, si no una mentira, entonces una verdad incompleta. Y aunque muchos de Uds. se prepararon para el 2000 de formas diferentes, estoy convencido de que están aquí porque cierta parte de ustedes ha hecho lo mismo que yo desde el origen de este nuevo siglo, desde que mi madre partiera, mi padre se apartara y mi Señor se rehusara a venir. Y extendí mi mano, buscando algo en que creer. Me aferré cuando llegué a Yale a los 18, con la fe de que mi viaje desde Oak Cliff, Texas fuera una oportunidad de dejar atrás los retos que había conocido, los sueños rotos y las almas deshechas que había visto. Pero cuando regresé a casa en unas vacaciones de invierno, con mi rostro estampado en el piso, mis manos atadas tras mi espalda y con un arma presionando mi cabeza, Supe que incluso la mejor educación no podía salvarme. Me aferré cuando me presenté en Lehman Brothers como practicante en el 2008. (Risas) Tan esperanzado... Que llamaba a casa para decir a mi familia que nunca más seríamos pobres. (Risas) Pero cuando vi que este templo financiero se venía abajo ante mis ojos, Supe que ni aún el mejor empleo podía salvarme. Me aferré al presentarme en Washington como un joven miembro de comité que había escuchado un llamado desde Illinois, que decía: «Ya ha pasado mucho tiempo, pero en esta elección, el cambio ha llegado a Estados Unidos». Pero cuando el Congreso se estancó en un punto, y el país se desmoronó y la fe y el cambio ya sabían a una cruel broma, Supe que aún la Segunda Venida Política no podría salvarme. Me había arrodillado fielmente ante el altar del Sueño Americano, rezando a los dioses de mi tiempo al dios del éxito, del dinero, y del poder. Pero una y otra vez, llegaba la medianoche, y yo abría mis ojos para ver que todos esos dioses habían muerto. Y desde ese cementerio, empezaba a buscar una vez más, no porque era valiente, sino porque sabía que bien podría creer o morir. Así que hice una peregrinación aún a otra Mecca, a Harvard Business School, (Risas) esta vez, sabiendo que no podía simplemente aceptar la salvación que afirmaba ofrecer. No, yo sabía que habría más trabajo que hacer. El trabajo empezó en el oscuro rincón de una concurrida fiesta, en la noche de un anticipado y triste invierno en Cambridge, cuando entre amigos nos hicimos la pregunta que los jóvenes en búsqueda de algo real se hacen por mucho tiempo: «¿Qué tal si hacemos un viaje largo?» (Risas) No sabíamos a dónde ir o cómo llegaríamos allí, pero sabíamos que teníamos que hacerlo Porque en nuestra vida anhelábamos, como Jack Kerouac escribió, «escabullirnos en la noche y desaparecer en algún lugar» y descubrir lo que todos hacían en todo el país. Así que aunque había otras voces que decían que el riesgo era muy alto y la ganancia muy baja, seguimos de cualquier forma. Recorrimos casi 13 000 km a lo largo de EE. UU. en el verano de 2013, cruzamos los pastizales de Montana, una Detroit desolada, los pantanos de Nueva Orleans, donde hallamos y trabajamos con hombres y mujeres dedicados a pequeños negocios que les rendían buenos resultados. Y al haber sido formado en el capitalismo occidental esto nos dio una idea revolucionaria. (Risas) Y esta idea se difundió, convirtiéndose en una ONG llamada MBA Across America, un movimiento que me trajo aquí al escenario de hoy. Esto se extendió porque descubrimos en esta generación un deseo de propósito, de sentido. Se extendió porque encontramos incontables emprendedores de costa a costa de Estados Unidos quienes estaban creando empleos, cambiando vidas y necesitaban un poco de ayuda. Pero si acaso soy honesto; se extendió también porque luché para difundirla. No había distancia a la cual no iba a predicar este mensaje, para contar con más gente que creyera que podríamos vendar las heridas de un país herido, en un negocio social al mismo tiempo. Pero era este viaje de evangelismo que me condujo a un evangelio muy diferente, que he venido a compartir con ustedes hoy. Empezó una noche hace casi un año en el Museo de Historia Natural de la Ciudad de Nueva York, en una gala para egresados de la Harvard Business School. Bajo una réplica a escala de una ballena, me senté con los titanes de nuestro tiempo mientras celebraban con sus colegas, sus hazañas. Había orgullo en ese salón donde el patrimonio neto y sus activos administrados sobrepasaban los 500 billones de dólares. Contemplamos todo lo que habíamos hecho, y era bueno. (Risas) Pero aconteció, que dos días después, tuve que viajar camino a Harlem, donde terminé estableciéndome en una granja urbana que una vez fue un lote baldío, escuchando a un hombre llamado Tony hablarme de los niños que se veían allí a diario. Todos ellos vivían bajo extrema pobreza. Muchos de ellos cargaban sus cosas en una mochila para evitar perderlas en un albergue. Algunos de ellos vinieron al programa de Tony, llamado Harlem Grown, para recibir la única comida que tenían cada día. Tony me contó que empezó Harlem Grown con dinero de su pensión, después de 20 años como taxista. Me contó que no se asignaba un salario, porque a pesar del éxito, el programa pasaba por apuros. Me contó que tomaría cualquier ayuda que pudiera conseguir. Y yo estaba allí como esa ayuda. Pero cuando dejé a Tony, sentí el ardor y el sabor de las lágrimas brotando de mis ojos. Sentí el pesar de la revelación que en una noche podía estar en un lugar, donde unos cientos de personas tenían 500 billones de dólares, y estar en otro lugar, dos días después, a sólo 50 cuadras de la carretera, donde un hombre iba sin pago alguno para que un niño tenga su única comida del día. Y no era la deslumbrante desigualdad la que me hacía querer llorar, no era la idea del hambre, de los niños sin hogar, no era odio hacia el 1% o pena hacia el 99%. No, yo estaba enfadado porque me había dado cuenta que yo era una diálisis para un país que necesitaba de un trasplante de riñón. Me di cuenta que mi historia representaba a todos aquellos que se esperaba que se levantaran por sus propios medios, aún cuando no tenían recurso alguno; vi que mi organización representaba toda la ayuda estructural y sistemática que nunca iba a Harlem o a Appalachia o al Noveno Distrito; que mi voz representaba todas esas voces que parecían tan incultas, tan descuidadas, tan desamparadas. Y lo triste de eso, era que la pena me cubría como la pena de sentarse frente al televisor, observando a Peter Jennings anunciar el nuevo milenio una y otra y otra vez más. Había sido engañado, embaucado, burlado, Pero esta vez, el falso salvador era yo. Verán, he recorrido un largo camino desde ese altar en la noche que creí que el mundo acabaría, de un mundo donde la gente hablaba en lenguas y veía el sufrimiento como un acto necesario de Dios y tomaba un texto como la verdad infalible. Sí, he llegado tan lejos que estoy exactamente de donde comencé. Porque simplemente no es cierto decir que vivimos en la era de la poca fe, no, hoy creemos tanto como en cualquier otro momento anterior a este. Algunos pueden creer en la profecía de Brené Brown o de Tony Robbins. Podemos creer en la biblia del New Yorker o de la revista Harvard Business Review. Podemos creer más profundamente cuando adoramos justo aquí en la iglesia de TED, pero queremos desesperadamente creer, Necesitamos creer. Hablamos en lenguas de carismáticos líderes que prometen resolver nuestros problemas. Vemos el sufrimiento como un acto necesario del dios del capitalismo, tomamos el texto del progreso tecnológico como la verdad infalible. Y difícilmente vemos el precio humano que pagamos cuando fallamos al cuestionar un ladrillo, porque tememos que pueda sacudir nuestros cimientos. Pero si están afectados por las cosas inadmisibles que hemos llegado a aceptar, entonces debe ser el tiempo de cuestionarse. Así que no tengo un evangelio de disrupción o innovación o de un triple objetivo. No tengo un evangelio de fe que compartir con ustedes hoy, de hecho. Tengo y ofrezco un evangelio de la duda.
The gospel of doubt does not ask that you stop believing, it asks that you believe a new thing: that it is possible not to believe. It is possible the answers we have are wrong, it is possible the questions themselves are wrong. Yes, the gospel of doubt means that it is possible that we, on this stage, in this room, are wrong. Because it raises the question, "Why?" With all the power that we hold in our hands, why are people still suffering so bad? This doubt leads me to share that we are putting my organization, MBAs Across America, out of business. We have shed our staff and closed our doors and we will share our model freely with anyone who sees their power to do this work without waiting for our permission. This doubt compels me to renounce the role of savior that some have placed on me, because our time is too short and our odds are too long to wait for second comings, when the truth is that there will be no miracles here. And this doubt, it fuels me, it gives me hope that when our troubles overwhelm us, when the paths laid out for us seem to lead to our demise, when our healers bring no comfort to our wounds, it will not be our blind faith -- no, it will be our humble doubt that shines a little light into the darkness of our lives and of our world and lets us raise our voice to whisper or to shout or to say simply, very simply, "There must be another way." Thank you. (Applause)
El evangelio de la duda no te pide que dejes de creer. te pide que creas algo nuevo: que es posible no creer. Es posible que nuestras respuestas estén mal, es posible de que las mismas preguntas estén erradas. Sí, el evangelio de la duda nos dice que es posible que nosotros, en este escenario, en este salón, estemos equivocados. Porque allí surge la pregunta: «¿Por qué?» Con todo el poder que poseemos en nuestras manos, ¿Por qué la gente aún está sufriendo tanto? Esta duda me lleva a compartir que mi organización, MBA Across America, la estamos cerrando. Hemos prescindido del personal y cerramos las puertas y compartiremos este modelo gratuitamente con cualquiera que se vea en poder de hacer este trabajo sin que esperen nuestro permiso. Este duda me obliga a renunciar al rol de salvador que algunos me han asignado, porque el tiempo es muy corto y las posibilidades muy grandes como para esperar Segundos Advenimientos, cuando la verdad es que aquí no habrá milagros. Y esta duda, me alimenta, me da esperanza que cuando los problemas nos agobien, cuando el camino dispuesto para nosotros parezca conducirnos a la muerte, cuando nuestros doctores no traigan confort a nuestras heridas, no será nuestra fe ciega, no, será nuestra humilde duda la que traiga una pequeña luz a la oscuridad de nuestras vidas y de nuestro mundo y nos permita alzar nuestra voz para susurrar, o para gritar o para decir sencillamente, muy sencillamente, «Debe haber otra forma». Gracias. (Aplausos)